<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A bride-bush, or A vvedding sermon compendiously describing the duties of married persons: by performing whereof, marriage shall be to them a great helpe, which now finde it a little hell.</title>
            <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837126</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837126</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14989)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 979:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A bride-bush, or A vvedding sermon compendiously describing the duties of married persons: by performing whereof, marriage shall be to them a great helpe, which now finde it a little hell.</title>
                  <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William Iaggard, for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the entrance into the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Whately.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1436:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1436:1"/>
            <p>A BRIDE-BVSH, OR A WEDDING SERMON:</p>
            <p>Compendiouſly deſcribing the duties of Married Perſons:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By performing whereof, Marriage ſhall</hi> be to them a great Helpe, which now finde it a little Hell.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Marriage is honourable amongſt all men: but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will iudge.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>William Iaggard,</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the entrance into the Royall Exchange, 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1436:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1436:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader; Marriage</hi> hath ſcarſe more that vſe, then that accuſe it. Moſt men enter into this eſtate, and beeing entred complaine therof. They ſhould rather complaine of themſelues. It is an vniuſt thing, and a fruit of ignorant pride, to caſt the blame of our greeuances vpon Gods ordinances. I had bene happie (ſaith one) had I not bene married. Then waſt thou fooliſh both before and ſince thy marriage. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe it well, it ſhall adde to thine happineſſe. We make bitter ſawce, and cry out that the meate is bitter. Thou liueſt in Matrimony not after Gods direction, but the rules (crooked rules they be) of thine owne luſts, and then ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, Oh that I had neuer married, Oh that I were vnmarried. For ſhame keepe ſilence, thy crying ſhewes thy diſeaſe. Thou art indeed married to an ill companion (thy wicked fleſh, that body of death, that old huſband) and art peſtered with its brood, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeekeſt a diuorce from this tyrant, nor endeauoureſt to crucify the wicked off-ſpring thereof. Hence are thy woes; not thy Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, not thy Wife, but thy pride, thy paſſion, cauſe all this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance, all this diſcontentment. I labour in this little Treatiſe to plead the cauſe of marriage: not ſo much directly in ſpeech, as indeede actually, by directing the married to the knowledge and practiſe of their duties, which would mend all. Theſe what ſoeuer man and woman indeuour to follow, if they prooue not marriage a ſolace to their ſoules, and refreſhing to their other greefes, let mee neuer but greeue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1436:3"/>
            <p>Theſe things I commend to thine vnderſtanding, to thy life: vſe them, and then ſay how thou ſpeedeſt. I intended them at firſt for a few, and now communicate them to many. It is no vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table (I am ſure) I hope, no vnprofitable deed. I deſire thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt make ſome vſe of them, therefore I make them publicke: if not, bee ignorant and complaine ſtill. I meane them not to the learned, that can finde out better directions for themſelues, but to thoſe whoſe place is not too good to learne of the meaneſt Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: euen vnto men of the ſame ranke, as they for the moſt part were, to whom I ſpake them. If this worke profite, I am glad, then I know it ſhall pleaſe: howſoeuer, thou haſt it Reader, and better ſhouldſt haue had, if my ſtore affoorded any better. I hope thou wilt not blame me for meaning well, and doing no harme. So I commend thee to the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Banburie,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt 20. 1608.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1436:3"/>
            <head>A BRIDE-BVSH: OR <hi>A Wedding Sermon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it were not growne out of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to preach without a text, I ſhould thinke that the fitteſt courſe for meetings of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. No one place of Scripture doth either directly containe, or plainly expreſſe the full dutie of the married couple: which yet from many places may well bee collected into the body of one diſcourſe. But leſt I ſhould ſeeme to affect nouelty, in recalling the long diſuſed pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of antiquity, I will make the ground of all my ſpeech, thoſe words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Epheſ. 5.23. where hee ſaith,</p>
            <q>The Huſband is the Wiues head.</q>
            <p>THe compariſon which the holy Ghoſt heere vſeth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords this generall point, That there is a mutuall bond of duty ſtanding betwixt man and wife. They are indebted each to other in a reciprocall debt. The parcels and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of which debt, I am at this time to declare vnto you for the direction of all ſuch as either are or ſhall be entred into this eſtate.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1436:4"/>
            <p n="2">2 Now that we may proceed in ſome order for the help of our owne and your memories, theſe duties are all of two kinds. Some be principall, ſome leſſe principall. Principall I terme thoſe, by the breach whereof this knot is diſſolued and quite vndone: and which being obſerued (other ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler infirmities notwithſtanding) the bond remaines entire on both ſides.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Theſe maine duties are two. The firſt is, the chaſte keeping of each ones body each for other. The Husband muſt not dare to giue himſelfe to any woman in this world but to his wife; nor the wife to company with any vnder heauen beſides her owne husband. Againſt which duty if either of them ſhall offend, the party ſo tranſgreſſing, hath committed adultery, broken the couenant of God, remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the yoke from the yoke fellowes neck, and laide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe open (if the Magiſtrate did as Gods law commands) to the bloody ſtroke of a violent death.<note place="margin">Leu. 20.40. Deut. 21.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if it be demanded, whether the party wronged may lawfully admit the other party againe, after the offence knowne: I anſwer, that in caſe the man or woman haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended once or ſo, through, infirmity, and yet beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted, ſhall by manifeſt outward tokens, teſtifie his or her repentance, and ſure deſire of amendment, then it is meet and conuenient that this offence bee by the yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low paſſed by: for the loue of the married couple ſhould be very feruent and abundant, and therefore able to paſſe by great, yea the greateſt wrongs, ſo farre as it may with ſafe conſcience be done. And we reade not of any expreſſe commandement which enioynes a finall ſeparation. But againe I ſay, that in caſe the party tranſgreſſing, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the begunne fault, and declare himſelfe irrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, the party thus iniuried is bound in conſcience both to complaine of the ſinne, and ſeparate himſelfe vtterly: for no man muſt make himſelfe a member of an harlot, nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of an whore-maſter. The chiefe thing therefore that married people muſt take heed of, is this, leſt by any means
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1436:4"/>they ſhould ſo farre offend God, neglect their publick co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, wrong their yoke-fellow, ſcandalize the Church, pollute their bodies, and aduenture their ſoules to damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to follow ſtrange fleſh, and receiue vnto the vſe of their bodies any beſides themſelues, whom God hath cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together, and ſanctified one for another. Yet not alone the groſſe act of adultery, but all ſuch ouer-familiar and light behauiours, as may giue either occaſion or ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an euill meaning, muſt be by them forborne &amp; ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; alwayes bearing in minde the graue ſpeech of wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6, 29.</note> [<hi>Whoſoeuer toucheth her</hi> (ſpeaking of his neighbors wife) <hi>ſhall not be innocent.</hi>] Let no man therfore, let no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man take this burning fire into their boſomes, or walk vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe ſcorching coales. And for the principall dutie ſo much.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The next is cohabitation or dwelling together, enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in expreſſe termes to the husband by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> (who bids him,<note place="margin">1 Peter 3, 7</note> 
               <hi>Dwell with his Wife</hi>) and therefore by good conſequent extending to her alſo: for who can dwel with a woman that will runne from him? And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> commands the husband to giue vnto the wife due beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7, 3.5.</note> and the wife to giue the ſame to the husband; which cannot be without this cohabitation: yea, he eſpecially for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids them to <hi>defraud each the other, vnleſſe it be by conſent, and afterwards to come together againe.</hi> Which doth neceſſarily import the abode in one home. So that the married man or woman may not abide or dwell where each of them plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but they muſt haue the ſame habitation as one bodie. I deny not, that the ſeruice of the countrey, and needefull priuate affaires, may cauſe a iuſt departure for (euen) a long time: but a wilfull and angry ſeparation of beds or houſes muſt not be tollerated. And if it ſo fall out, that either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doe frowardly and peruerſty withdraw him or herſelfe from this matrimoniall ſociety (which fault is tearmed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion) the man or woman thus offending, doth ſo far vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the couenant of marriage, that (the thing being found
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1436:5"/>incureable, through the obſtinacie of that party, after iuſt care had to redreſſe it) the other is looſed from the former band, and may lawfully (after an orderly proceeding with the Church or Magiſtrate in that behalfe) ioyne him or her ſelfe to another. Of which there is very great reaſon. Firſt, becauſe ſuch a ſeparation is a wilful fruſtrating of the proper purpoſe &amp; end of matrimony, annihilating the ſame through his default and ſinnefulneſſe (euen preſumptuous) which is found guilty, and for this cauſe deſerueth (yea conſtraineth) that hee ſhould bee reiected, as no longer a yoke-fellow. Secondly, becauſe ſuch vnfaithfull deſertion is almoſt neuer ſeparated from adultery, as the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateth in the forenamed place, ſaying, <hi>Leſt Satan tempt you for your incontinency.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7, 5.</note> Hee doth vnauoidably caſt himſelfe vpon vncleanneſſe that ſo lewdly caſts off marriage, which he might auoide. And for this matter, wee haue receyued cleare direction from the holy Ghoſt by the Apoſtle, who ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>If the vnbeleeuer depart, let him depart: a brother or a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is not bound in ſuch thing.</hi> In which words, he permits not to the vnbeleeuer ſuch ſeparations as lawfull, but caſts the fault vpon him alone, and after frees the other party from the band by which he or ſhee was formerly tied: as if hee had ſaide; If he will needes be gone, let him; and trouble not your ſelues about it, the ſin lyes wholly vpon his owne ſoule. A Chriſtian man or woman, when caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fall out, is no longer tied to the former couenant, nor to the former partie, which hath himſelfe firſt broken it. Neither is this any whit contrary to that of our Sauiour, who forbids a man to put away his wife &amp; marry another, vnleſſe it be for adultery.<note place="margin">Matth. 19, 9.</note> For we allow not to him or her, any ſuch liberty of putting away, but vpon that only cauſe. Yet if he or ſhe be wrongfully put away (the yoke-fellow withdrawing him or herſelfe out of the way, ſo that there be no hope to recall them, or elſe not returning vpon good perſwaſion or meanes vſed) we yeelde with the Apoſtle, a freedome to the party ſo wronged. And theſe things you ſee may well ſtand together. No man may lawfully forſake
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1436:5"/>his wife, nor the wife the husband (but in caſe of adultery) to marry another; and yet any man or woman, being wrongfully forſaken by his or her yoke-fellow, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully then marry another, as being disburdened of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer yoke, without any ſinne, on their parts, in that thing, procuring it. Onely we profeſſe, that in caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a iuſt and orderly courſe muſt bee taken. Euery one may not headdily, and vpon a ſudde, carue to themſelues: but ſeeke direction, and craue helpe from the Church and Magiſtrate, whoſe dutie bindes them to prouide remedy for ſuch inconueniences. So that this thing alſo muſt bee diligently auoided by married people, that they doe neuer vpon occaſion of diſcontentment, or the like, abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or runne away from each other; which to doe, were to vntie that knot, which God before had knit betwixt them, and to ſeparate the things which God (and man by Gods allowance) had conioyned. Yea, they muſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone beware of making an vtter rent and totall breach in their ſociety, but auoid alſo thoſe ſmaller iarres and cracks, that make way thereunto. They muſt not through paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate fallings out, and proud diſtaſting of each others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, ſeparate houſe, bed or table, no not for a ſhort ſpace. They muſt not ſeeke occaſions of long and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe abſence, through careleſneſſe or ſlight reſpect each of other, or following vaine pleaſures and company-keeping abroad. For, is it not a madnes to procure a ſtrangeneſſe betwixt themſelues, which ought to bee moſt familiar? And were it not better, not to depart, than to make an open iarre of that which might haue beene priuately reconciled?</p>
            <p n="5">5. And for the maine and principall duties required in matrimony, viz. chaſtity and cohabitation, ſo much. The leſſe principall follow, to which, men and women are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed bound by their promiſe and vow, but yet not with ſo much ſtrictnes, that any offence in them ſhould make the former bargaine voide: wants in theſe matters, doe ſtretch the corn of matrimony, and giue (as I may ſay) a ſore gird
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1436:6"/>vnto it, but breake it not: onely they breake Gods Commaundement exceedingly, that haue not in theſe things alſo great care to confirme that vnion, which ſhould bee made indiſſoluble, by their diligence. Now theſe alſo are of two ſorts, whereof the firſt reſpecteth their ordinary ſociety; the ſecond looketh to the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the marriage-bed. Againe, thoſe which concerne their ordinary ſociety, are of two ſorts: Some bee mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, pertayning to both: others ſpeciall pertayning to eyther of them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The mutuall therefore (that wee may ſpeake of them in order) are requyred both of man and wife, though not in an equall meaſure of both. For in all theſe common duties, the husband ſhould bee moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant, knowing that more of euery grace is looked for from him, then from the weaker veſſell. Wee call them not therefore common or mutuall, becauſe both ſhould haue a like quantity of them; but becauſe both muſt haue ſome of all, and the husband moſt of all. And for theſe common duties, you muſt know in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that whatſoeuer is requyred of all men and women, generally towards other, by the Law of Chriſtianity and Charity, as they bee men and neighbors; the ſame is in an higher degree and larger meaſure requyred from the husband toward the wife, and from her to him. So that looke what the Law of Loue or Religion bids thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to any perſon, as a man or Chriſtian, that it bindes thee much more diligently and carefully to performe to thy yoke-fellow. The neerer band of matrimony weakens not, but confirmes the more common of humanity. But it ſhalbe needfull more particularly to deſcribe theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon duties.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They bee of two kindes: The former reſpecting themſelues; the latter their families. Vnto themſelues they owe in common; firſt loue; ſecondly, faithfulneſſe and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1436:6"/>helpefulneſſe; ioyned together, a faithfull helpefulneſſe, and an helpefull faithfulneſſe. As for loue, it is the life, the ſoule of marriage, without which it is no more it ſelfe, than a carcaſe is a man; yea, it is vncomfortable, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and a liuing death. For this, all muſt labour, as all will yeeld, that take marriage vpon them. The want of this, cauſeth defectiueneſſe in all other duties: the abundance of it, ſupplyeth what is wanting in the reſt. Loue ſeaſons and ſweetens all eſtates: Loue breakes off, and compoſeth all controuerſies: Loue ouer-ruleth all affections, it ſquareth all actions; in a word, it is the King of the heart, which, where it preuayleth, marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is it ſelfe indeede, viz. a pleaſing combination of two perſons, into one home, one purſe, one heart, and one fleſh. But to commend it, and the good effects of it, (which all doe confeſſe) were needleſſe paynes. Let vs rather ſhewe what a kinde of loue it muſt bee, and how it may bee gotten.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This loue therefore which wee ſpeake of, muſt bee firſt ſpirituall, then matrimoniall. Spirituall I ſay, that is, grounded principally vpon the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God that requyres it, (for I ſpeake of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) not vpon the face, fauour, proportion, beauty, dowrie, nobility, gifts or good parts of him or her, to whom it is due: for that naturall loue which builds it ſelfe vpon ſuch ſandy conſiderations, as the fore-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, will either bee blowne downe by ſome ſtorme or tempeſt of diſpleaſure, or fall of it ſelfe, or elſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into iealouſie, the moſt deuouring and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting canker that can harbour in a married perſons breſt: but ſpirituall loue, that lookes vpon God, reſts vpon his will, yeeldes to his Commaundement, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues to obey it, cannot change it ſelfe, becauſe the cauſe thereof is vnchangeable. Thou loueſt thy Wife, for that ſhee is faire, well-ſpoken, courteous, of good feature, brings much, and is huſwifely. It is well.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1436:7"/>But what will become of thy loue, when all thoſe things faile, as all may, the moſt muſt faile? Thou loueſt thine husband, becauſe hee is a proper man, and hath an actine and able body, is of good health, wit, carriage; becauſe hee is kinde, louing, of faire condition, vſeth thee well. But where ſhall we finde thy loue, if an alteration come to theſe things, as to all earthly things it may come? Loe then how there is no conſtancy or firmitude in other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But he which loues his wife, and ſhee which loues her husband, becauſe God hath ſo bidden, the maker of all things hath enioyned it, the Lord and Maſter of the heart, who alone may command the very affections, appoints it ſo; ſhall finde his or her loue laſting and durable, as God alters not, and his Law continues alwayes the ſame. This right foundation of loue, is Gods Commandement, and then it is ſpirituall when built vpon this rocke.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It muſt be alſo matrimoniall: Wee are to loue our friends, our kindred, our neighbours, yea forreiners, and our vtter enemies, euen all men euery-where: but the nuptiall loue of yoke-fellowes, is a ſpeciall and peculiar loue, farre more deare and inward than all, or any of all theſe. It is the fixing of their hearts in the good liking each of other, as the onely fit and good match that could bee found vnder the Sunne for them. The husband muſt reſt his heart in his wife, as the beſt wife that the world could haue yeelded him. The wife muſt ſettle her very ſoule vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her husband, as the beſt husband that might haue beene had amongſt men for her. Thus doing, they ſhould loue perfectly; thus ſtriuing to doe, they loue intirely. They may lawfully thinke others better men or women, but none a better husband or wife for them than their yoke-fellow: for this were to admit the deſire of changing, which cannot ſtand with true loue. Who would change his Childe with any man? Euery mans owne ſon pleaſeth him beſt, though perhaps his qualities diſpleaſe; ſo ſhould the husband, ſo the wife. They therefore that are ſtill vpbraiding each
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1436:7"/>other with the by-paſt matches, which they might, or ſhould haue had, loue not ſoundly, though they may ſmile vpon each other. Marriage-loue admits of no equall, but placeth the yoke-fellow next of all to the ſoule of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty louing; it will know none dearer, none ſo deare. And of this quality is the loue we require.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But how ſhall one that wants this loue, attaine it, and he which hath ſome portion thereof, gaine a larger increaſe? I anſwere, there bee two things which will euen cement and glew the foules of man and wife together; the firſt is, that they take ſpeciall notice of Gods gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, for good in their match. They which looke to God as the match-maker, and that in fauour take each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as loue-tokens from Heauen, and therefore cannot but loue that well, which comes as a ſigne of his fauour, whom they ſtriue to loue aboue all. But they which ſee not his hand mercifully coupling them in this fellowſhip, muſt needes fall out ſpeedily, ſeeing they want this third thing, as it were the ligament and iuncture of their affections. A matter of ſmall value is not ſmally reſpected, when it comes in good-will, from a great friend, and deare withall. Hee that loues the giuer, will loue his gift alſo, though not ſo pretious: So the husband or wife. though not of the beſt parts, ſhalbe deare to the yoke-fellow that loues God, if he or ſhe reſolue in their hearts, God in great goodneſſe hath beſtowed this man or woman vpon mee. Yea, ſay hee or ſhe be ſomewhat froward and ſullied (as I may ſay) with ill conditions, the deareneſſe of the giuer wil counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ſome blemiſhes in the gift. Say the Lord did correct thee, in giuing thee this husband, this wife: It was in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and for thy good. Canſt thou chuſe but kiſſe and loue euen the rod that comes from a fathers hand? But to this meanes adde a ſecond (which will alſo further vnto this) and loue ſhall grow without faile: Let married cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ioyne together in priuat prayer, good conference, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalmes, and other like religious exerciſes betwixt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1436:8"/>themſelues alone.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> would not haue the prayers of the married interrupted: for hee knew full well, that theſe were the beſt meanes of nouriſhment to their loues. In theſe things, the bright beames of Gods Image will ſhine forth, which haue power to make them amiable each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Heere they ſhall bring ſo much profite and good to each others ſoule, euen to their owne feelings, as will effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually prouoke their affections to bee mutually feruent. Heere they ſhall ſee themſelues to bee children of the ſame father, ſeruants of one Maſter, ſtrangers of one Countrey, &amp; Pilgrims trauailing both to one &amp; the ſame home. So when the ſudden land-floud of youthfull &amp; violent affections are quite dryed vp, theſe fountaines of ſpirituall loue, which prayer, and other exerciſes of Religion ſhall haue digged, will ſtill runne with a more moderate and ſober, but yet more laſting and conſtant ſtreame. Let them ſeaſon their naturall ſociety with this ſpirituall communion, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſeruing of God, and they ſhall auoyde the ſurfet of ſatiety, which choaketh loue. Religion will knit the hearts of ſtrangers faſt in one, making them deare to each other euer after, that for the ſpace but of one moneth or weeke, ſhall conuerſe and ioyne together in the ſame; how much more effectuall will it bee to faſten their ſoules that are tyed with ſo many and perpetuall bandes beſides? Therefore to you all that are, to you that ſhall bee hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and wiues, bee this deliuered as a direction; which if you faile to obſerue, you heare without profite. Pray together one with and for another in ſecret; conferre, reade the Word of God together, and ſing Pſalmes alone: this will ſo riuet your hearts, that no contention ſhall diſſeuer them. For if you doe fall to ſome actions of vnkindneſſe, when you meete together againe in prayer, in ſtead of faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting each other, the husband will blame himſelfe, the wife herſelfe: ſhe comming in Gods preſence, wil ſee the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her owne ſinnes, hee of his, and then the offences one of another ſhall appeare but ſmall. Thus they ſhall bee aſhamed after to iarre, conſidering they muſt ſhame
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1436:8"/>themſelues before God for iarring: ſo that if any grudge ariſe, prayer will heale and compoſe the ſame, that it doe not feſter, rankle, or grow to a continued hard conceite. And let euery man aske counſell of his owne heart, if the little praying together of husbands and wiues, the ſeldome ioyning together in any good exerciſes, be not the true cauſe of their little loue. Fond hee or ſhee may bee, that pray not betweene themſelues, louing they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And for the firſt common dutie thus much. The ſecond is faithfulneſſe, and helpefulneſſe conioyned.<note place="margin">Prou. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſayth, that <hi>the Husbandes heart may truſt in his Wife.</hi> If ſhee bee a good Wife, ſhee muſt bee truſtie to him, how much more hee to her? Hee ſayth alſo, that <hi>ſhee will doe him good all the dayes of her life.</hi> It was the ende of her creation to bee an helper: hee muſt bee a greater helper to her, and doe more good, by how much his place is better. Now theſe two gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are well vnited, when they bee carefull, not to doe themſelues, or ſuffer (through their careleſneſſe, or wittingly) to bee done by any other, any manner of hurt each to other; and when they bee diligent, ſo farre as in them lyes, to doe, and procure by others to bee done, all good one to another. Now, man and wife muſt bee thus faithfull, and helpefull; firſt to each others foule, in wife and due care, to heale each others faults, and chiefly to preuent the ſame. If the Husband liue in any groſſe ſinne, the Wife muſt labour by all kinde, louing, and Chriſtian meanes to draw him out of it: which, if her own skill faile to effect, ſhe muſt procure a Phyſician for his ſoule, as ſhe would doe for his body, being ſick &amp; diſeaſed. Only, if after all good meanes vſed, he proue a dog, a ſwine, that gru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; barks, &amp; regards no admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe hath now diſcharged her duty, &amp; for the reſt, muſt wait and pray to God, the great Phyſician of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1436:9"/>ſoule to redreſſe the matter, enioying ſtill in the meane this comfort, that ſhe hath vſed the beſt meanes with faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to procure his amendment. And ſo muſt the husband alſo deale with the wife: yea, they muſt both obſerue the dyet, temper, and conſtitution (as I may ſpeake) of each others ſoule, till they perceiue what infirmities they be ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially inclined and ſubiect vnto, that ſo hee may with-draw from her, ſhe from him, all occaſions and prouocations to that euill, and ſhun all occaſions that might cauſe them ſo to ouer-ſhoot themſelues. And againe, that they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all meanes to weaken and hinder the ouer-flowing of ſuch faults, and to ſtay them from extremity, if they haue begunne to ſlip therein. They muſt labour to be thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the diſeaſes and diſtemperatures of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers hearts, not to vpbraide, not to diſgrace, not to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, but to helpe and ſupport one another, by diligent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding all things, which will cauſe ſuch euils to breake out, and vſing whatſoeuer will heale or mitigate the ſame. So that they deſerue to bee condemned as treacherous and vntruſty to one another, that for their owne eaſe ſake, will quietly permit their yoke-fellowes to ſleepe in any ſinne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. Let the ſoule of the husband be infected with ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, with breach of the Sabbath, with vniuſtice, or any ſuch like; the wife feares an angry paſſion, if ſhe ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him, and holds her peace; and ſo deales he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with her. Is not this to betray one another to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and damnation? to ſuffer one another goe to hell in quiet? And they be alſo moſt harmefull and miſchieuous yoke-fellowes, that are ready to ſpy into the frailties of one another, with an euill and malicious eye, to vpbraide, to prouoke, to vexe one another. If hee perceiue his wife to bee paſſionately inclined, hee is in heate, and will doe this and this to vexe her; ſhee alſo will doe ſo and ſo to anger him: ſo that what infirmities they eſpy, as it were gawled places, or ſores, one vpon another, they loue to fret, chafe &amp; rubbe the ſame, and make them worſe. Sorry helpe it is, that ſuch perſons afforde vnto the ſoules of their married
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1436:9"/>companions. But they muſt be helpefull alſo, and faithfull to each others body, by a free and ready vnder-going any coſt or paines (to their power) to procure whatſoeuer dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, Phyſick, or other-like neceſſaries, may make for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of health, and preuenting or remedying of ſicknes. He muſt not thinke any paines or charges too much, that is this way beſtowed (with wiſedome, and according to his power) vpon her; nor ſhe, which is ſpent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. They muſt auoide that niggardice, which poſſeſſeth many folks harts, that they cannot finde in their hearts to allow one another, fire, candle, food conuenient, or the expence of Phyſicke, when ſickneſſe commeth. This is not to be helpfull, but to doe harme rather: and argues a moſt vnlouing diſpoſition. Thirdly, they muſt bee careful of others good name, that they preſerue it by honeſt ſecrecie and concealement. They muſt ſhunne, as a monſtrous treacherie, the publiſhing of one anothers faults and frailties, or the diſcouering of one anothers ſecrets; I meane thoſe things, which, in hope of priuacie, they haue communicated one to another. The wife is worthy all hard meaſure, that ſpreads abroad euery thing which ſhee ſees amiſſe in her husband, ſtill complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and crying out in euery company, what an ill match ſhe hath met withall. And that husband cannot be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with bad vſage ſufficiently anſwerable to his deſerts, that can finde almoſt none other talke, but what a bad wife he hath light vpon. Theſe bee ill birds, that defile their owne neſts, and franticke folke, that vncouer each others nakednes, and throw dirt in each others faces. When man and wife fall to peaching, what ſoule loathes it not? If they that be inward in ſuch a degree ſeeke to deface their names mutually; what man, what woman can bee free from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch? Yea, they muſt not onely couer each others naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, but alſo conceale each others ſecrets. For, if whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he tels her, ſhe will talke of to another, by this meanes it comes to another, and ſo ſucceſſiuely to a fourth and fift, till that thing be (to his griefe) made publick to the whole towne, that he left in his wiues boſome, as it were vnder
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1436:10"/>the locke and key of truſtineſſe, and he doe the like to her; what peace can they haue, what concord? How can they auoyde, but ſuch occaſions will bring forth diſcontentment and diſſention? There can bee no quiet and comfortable liuing, where there is not vſe of concealement and ſecrecy. Now therefore, let theſe parts of faithfulneſſe and helpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, to the ſoules, bodies, and names one of another, be commended to all married people, which deſire to enioy themſelues in this eſtate.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And now hauing ſpoken of that ranke of common duties, which concerne their owne perſons, I come to them which concerne their families and houſholds. For men and women that before were parts of ſome other family, doe therefore marry, that they may bee the chiefe of a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and begetting children, (and trayning them vp, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſeruants, according to their place) may ſtore the world with people, and prouide plants, as it were, for the Church, Gods owne Vineyard. Wherefore they ſhall not haue thorowly diſcharged their duty, by performing all the afore-mentioned things mutually to themſelues, vnleſſe they regard their families alſo; wherein the husband, as the firſt mouer and chiefe; the wife as a ſubordinate and good furtherer, muſt both ioyne together for good. Theſe things themſelues which ſhall bee named. I confeſſe to belong to them, as they be gouernors, &amp; ſtand in relation to ſeruants and children; but the ioyning together in them is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I would preſſe, as a part of their marriage-duty. Now this their family they muſt maintaine and gouerne, keepe it, and guide it,</p>
            <p n="13">13. For maintenance therefore: firſt, both muſt be labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and induſtrious in their calling, and ſet themſelues with diligence to doe ſomthing, for which their family may fare the better. The husband muſt not be a drone, and make his wife a drudge. The wife muſt not giue her ſelfe to lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and caſt all the paines &amp; care vpon her husband: but he in things that concerne him without; &amp; ſhe (in things that concerne her moſt within) muſt vnite their paines for their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1436:10"/>profite. If either liue idly as a doe-nothing, that party is a burden, &amp; (as a gowty leg, or diſeaſed member) troubles &amp; moleſts an whole houſhold, <hi>Salomon</hi> hath much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the painfulnes of a good huſwife, &amp; he hath alſo ſpoken more then once, in commendation of a good diligent hand, for the mans part. They muſt therefore ioyne as partners in labouring. Secondly, they muſt ioyne in honeſt and thrifty ſauing, from coſt &amp; needles expences: They muſt not pinch from Mercy and Iuſtice, but ſaue from prodigality and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending. He muſt not caſt away the goods in gaming and following the Ale-houſe &amp; Tauerne, or other places of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifty meetings: neither muſt ſhe be lauiſh to her talking goſſips: but both muſt auoyde that ſinne, which declares a man to be worſe euen then an Infidell; I meane, not caring for them of his owne houſhold. They muſt neither nouriſh ſweet toothes, or finiſh &amp; coſtly backs (theſe be theeues:) they muſt neither make priuate purſes for themſelues, or let all things goe at randome as they come, but vnite their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours for the common benefite, as the right hand &amp; the left. Thirdly, they muſt haue a common care, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no neceſſary thing, through their default &amp; improuidence be wanting to their family in time of neede; no hurtfull thing come vpon them at vnawares. They muſt ioine in foreſight &amp; due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, what is or may be needfull and vſefull for them, to the end it may be procured; and what dangerous, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it. Two eyes ſee more then one: and for this intent they bee linked in ſo neare and cloſe a fellowſhip, that they may bee but as one in all theſe things, in labour, thrift and fore-ſight: which whileſt they doe, the Lord will bleſſe their endeauours, and their hands ſhall finde abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. Otherwiſe the idle perſon walkes vpon an hedge of thornes, which ſhall ſurely pricke his feete. The vnwiſe and vnthrifty perſon thruſts his foote into the ſnare that will intangle him, neither ſhall they euer bee without vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diſquietment, diſcontent and brawlings, that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thoſe duties. Alwayes prouided, that they bee both moderate in this matter. For, if they fall to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1436:11"/>pinching, carking, coueting, and eager affecting of wealth; Heauen and earth cannot keepe a family diſeaſed with this dropſie, from many ſicke, troubleſome and froward fittes.</p>
            <p n="14">14. But what ſhall it auaile to maintaine a familie, without gouernment; or how can it bee gouerned but by them? ſo that they muſt alſo bee good rulers at home, and ioyne in guiding the houſhold: the man as Gods immediat officer, and the King in his family: the woman as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie ſubordinate, and aſſociate to him, but not altogether equall; and both in their order muſt gouerne. Now to this end, their firſt care muſt be to ſee, that Religion flouriſh in their families, and bee truely planted in their ſeruants and children; by their care to catechize them, to reade the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and call vpon the name of God in the midſt of them. And that they being inſtructed, may grow further; they muſt alſo bring them to the publick aſſemblies; examining them alſo of their profiting by thoſe meanes. Theſe things, the husband being preſent, muſt performe; and the wife in his abſence, and both muſt haue care to finde conuenient time for the ſame; wherein if hee grow ſlacke, ſhee muſt helpe him, and hee her. Better (in reſpect of themſelues) keepe no family, then a family of little diuels; and ſuch ſhall they be without Gods more then ordinary worke and grace, if they performe not theſe things. He keepes an houſhold of fiends, a Seminary for the diuell, a nurcerie for hell and the kingdome of death, which is not carefull by theſe fore-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med meanes, to make his children and ſeruants become ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and children to God. Which, how often it falles out, wofull experience can teſtifie. Sometimes the husband would haue God ferued in the family; the wife hangs off, and counts it loſt time. Sometimes the wife deſires to haue the worſhip of God finde place vnder the roofe; and hee like a profane beaſt calles it preciſenes, and will not haue an houre ſo ill ſpent. Sometimes both conſpire in negligence &amp; omiſſion: but how ſeldome doe their deſires and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours meete in this moſt needfull point? How ſeldome do
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1436:11"/>they one prouoke, animate and incourage one another in ſo profitable workes? This is the fountaine of all diſorder in families; where God is not ſerued, what can abound but impiety and profaneneſſe, in Maſter, Miſtris, ſeruants, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the whole houſhold? But now, let all that feare God take care, that they faile not in vſing all good meanes to eſtabliſh Religion and the exerciſes of it in their houſes, remembring with feare that curſe, which the Prophet prayes God may come vpon the family,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.25.</note> wherein his Name is not called vpon. Secondly, they muſt ouer-ſee the wayes of their family.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.27.</note> This thing <hi>Salomon</hi> commendeth in the vertuous wife, by a word worthy noting, which ſignifies to ſtand as a watch-man in a watch tower, to looke on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide, that no enemy doe ſurpriſe the ſame at vnawares. So ſhe doth diligently looke into the behauiour of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the roofe, that no diſordered nor ſinfull practice may finde quiet entrance and abode there: and it were a great ſhame for the husband, if the wife ſhould exceede him in this watchfulneſſe. Both of them muſt vſe their eyes with care then, to preuent all idleneſſe and wickedneſſe in their ſeruants and children, and to looke that they faithfully doe their buſines committed to them, and carry themſelues Chriſtianly towards one another, and all men. If inferiors of themſelues would bee carefull enough of their carriage, what neede a gouernour in an houſe? But God knowing that the beſt ſeruants, and the beſt children, will not want infirmities, yea, will be many wayes ſubiect to infirmities, as idlenes, twatling, diſcord, and many of the like nature; would that the Maſter and Miſtris ſhould haue their eyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to preuent the ſame ſeruants Children muſt bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, their behauiour muſt be obſerued, they muſt be ſet to worke, and the eye of the gouernours, with their care conioyned, muſt effect it, or elſe the family ſhall proue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, be the gouernours for other things neuer ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thirdly, they muſt ioyne together in admoniſhing, or incouraging; in reprouing, or if neede be, alſo correcting their inferiours. And in theſe things both muſt be carefull
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1436:12"/>to maintayne each others authority to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> full. If one do think it meet to encorage any in the family with ſome little kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that is fit, the other muſt not ſeeme to grudge at it, or be vnwilling. If the one wil reproue, the other muſt not defend. When the husband goes about to correct the children, the wife muſt not grow angry &amp; ſaue them, as if ſhe thought it much to haue them kept vnder nurture; neither muſt he doe ſo towards her. Suppoſe either of them exceed, chiding or correcting without cauſe, or aboue the meaſure that agrees to the fault: the other muſt then quietly ſpeake of it in the abſence of the inferior, &amp; not make a braule about it before their faces, as it were bolſtering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out againſt the authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of the yoke-fellow. For if he doe, and ſhe vndoe; or if ſhe correct, &amp; he cocker; what will be the fruite, but heart-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and diſtemper betwixt themſelues, &amp; contempt firſt of one, after both their authorities from the party to whom they haue ſhewed themſelues ſo indiſcreete? So at length, as in a Boate, wherein all the weight lyes vpon one ſide, the whole family wilbe turned ouer into the waues of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtrife: whereas if they did ſit together in good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to further the fruite of one anothers admonitions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, corrections, exhortations or incouragements; they ſhould both preſerue their owne authority in the family, and keepe peace betweene themſelues, and finde good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment in their inferiours by theſe meanes. And for the common duties of man &amp; wife to themſelues &amp; their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, for maintaining &amp; gouerning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thus much. We come now to ſpeake of thoſe that are peculiar to either of them.</p>
            <p n="15">15. And firſt I will informe the man; then the woman after. Now for the husbands ſpeciall duties, they may fitly be referred to theſe two heads: The keeping of his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the vſing of it. Firſt, he muſt keepe his authority, and maintaine himſelfe in that place, wherein his Maker hath ſet him. Nature hath framed the lineaments of his body to ſuperiority, &amp; ſet the print of gouernment in his face, which is more ſterne, leſſe delicate then the womans. He muſt not ſuffer this order of nature to be inuerted. The Lord in his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1436:12"/>Word cals him the head; hee muſt not ſtand lower than the ſhoulders; if he doe, that is a deformed family. It is a ſin to come lower than God hath ſet one. It is not humility, but baſenes, to be ruled by her whom he ſhould rule. No Gene rall would thanke the Captaine, for ſurrendring his place to ſome common ſouldier: nor will God the husband, for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the wife to beare the ſway. The authority is Gods, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted in his perſon; he muſt not commit, that it bee troden downe &amp; deſpiſed. But, will ſome man ſay, my wife is diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered &amp; froward, how ſhal I then hold mine own? It is ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſaid than done, if a man meete with women of ſtirring ſpirits: direct vs therefore how to do it. I anſwer, that moſt men do wrongfully caſt the blame vpon their wiues, of abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their authority, when it is due to themſelues alone. It is not extorted from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiues violence, but caſt away, &amp; loſt by their owne folly &amp; indiſcretion. Know then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in this ſociety, muſt not be kept by maine force, and by violence, but by skil: not by big looks, &amp; great words, &amp; cruel behauiour, as of a great maſtiffe towards a ſilly curre; but by a milder &amp; more artificiall courſe. And that you may practiſe it, this it is. Firſt, the husband muſt giue a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, walking vprightly, Chriſtianly, ſoberly, religiouſly in his family. The wife muſt needes then giue him the better place, if he ſhew himſelf to be the better perſon. No inferior can chuſe but in his hart ſtoop to that ſuperior, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace &amp; Gods Image do appeare. A vertuous man ſhalbe regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in the conſcience euen of the worſt woman: yea, &amp; in her behauior alſo, if ſhe be not monſtrous. A godly wiſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage will draw good reſpect, &amp; willing ſubiection, neither can any man bring forth one thus qualified, troden down in contempt. In a mad fit &amp; paſſionate diſtemper, the wife of the beſt may ſling forth, &amp; be vndutifull, but afterwards her hart will condemne her ſelfe, &amp; iuſtifie him, and ſo he loſeth not authority, though it bee aſſaulted; yea, he recouers his owne with aduantage. And as in generall, wee preſcribe a godly conuerſation in the family, to bee the preſeruer and vpholder of the mans authority; ſo ſpecially muſt hee be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1436:13"/>counſelled to ſhunne and abandon three ſpeciall and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull euils, that haue this effect, to make euery man ſeeme vile and baſe in all eyes that behold him thus defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The firſt is bitterneſſe: So <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the husband; <hi>Bee not bitter.</hi> The ſauour of violent and raging paſſions, wil ſmell ſo lothſomely in the wiues noſtrils, comming from the husband, that ſhe ſhal hardly chuſe, but firſt hate him, and deſpiſe him after. This diſtaſteful bitterneſſe of ſpeech and behauiour, bewrayes impotency of affection, and that great want of wiſdome; and this will produce great want of reuerence. If thou be an husband, and wouldeſt bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, tumble not thy ſelfe in thoſe foule, dirty and ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guzzels of paſſionate rayling, ſtryking, or the like. That which bewrayes ſo great folly, muſt it not procure exceeding great contempt? Secondly, beware of vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, that is another great enemy to authority, and as a worme, rottes and conſumes the ſame. Whatſoeuer man giues himſelfe to drinking, gaming, ill-company keeping, (which three vices go commonly together) ſhall at once loſe his wit, wealth, eſtimation. When drinke hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed reaſon, gaming prouidence, ill-company good conditions; the carriage wilbe fooliſh, wicked, beaſt-like, and the perſon baſe, hated, loathed. Neuer did vnthrift keepe his place, as not his money. For who can regard him that will not be worth any thing? Thirdly, lightnes muſt be auoyded, fooliſh behauiour and carriage, chyldiſh and vnſober trickes, that haue no print or ſtampe of grauity vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; theſe expoſe a man to contempt. For if the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band put on a fooles Coate, and take a bable in his hand, (and what elſe be theſe odde and toyiſh demeanures?) can hee blame his wife, though ſhee take vp laughter at him? The bitter man is as a franticke head, troubleſome: the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifty man as a ſcald head, fulſome: the light man, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as a giddy head, ridiculous. Such will ſoone diſpleaſe themſelues, though none goe about to vndermyne them. But l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t euery godly man abhorre theſe baſe euils, and ſtriue for holyneſſe of conuerſation, that hee may bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1436:13"/>a gouernour, and his ſuperiority remaine entire vnto him.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Yet what auailes to keepe authority, if hee vſe it not? or how can it but ruſt without vſing? Wherefore the husband muſt exerciſe his authority, and wee muſt direct him for that purpoſe. Now, to the intent he may gouerne well, it behoues him to know both the end of his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the manner of it, The end of this, as all other go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, in Nations, Kingdomes, Countries, Cities and Townes, is not the ſatisfying of his deſires, or procuring of his eaſe, pleaſure, credit, which hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefedome: (for then all things runne out of order, as when a bowle is not ſet with a right byas:) but the good and benefit of the party gouerned, to the glory of God the chiefe Lord and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all. Thus one thing alone being well obſerued, would ſtoppe out a great ſtreame of inconueniences, from breaking in vpon the family: For therefore moſt men go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne not well, becauſe they doe wholly ſerue themſelues in gouerning, and not the wife; therefore they will doe any thing to pleaſe their owne humors, though it bee neuer ſo dangerous to the wife (which is the greateſt abſurdity in gouernment that can bee committed,) becauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the place was giuen them to fulfill their owne deſires, and not ſo much to procure their wiues good; which conceit is altogether falſe. For as the Miniſters muſt watch ouer the ſoules of their flocke for their profite and ſaluation, not for their own priuate wealth and aduantage: ſo muſt the husband deale with his wife: for this is the end why God hath ordained gouernours, priuate and publique vnder him, that the inferiours might the better bee drawne vnto him by meanes of them, which alwayes ſhould be (as they be called) their betters.</p>
            <p n="17">17. And yet to intend this, if he doe not in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure attaine it, were to little purpoſe: ſo that as hee muſt aime at her good, ſo muſt hee effect it, by gouerning in a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1436:14"/>right manner, to the nouriſhing and encreaſing of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vertue, rooting out and weakning of whatſoeuer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption hee ſhall meete with in her. Now then hee rules in a right manner, when in ruling, he rules himſelfe by three principall vertues, which are of greateſt vſe and note in all gouernments, and in this domeſticall kingdome, as I may ſo terme it.</p>
            <p n="18">18. The firſt of theſe three vertues is wiſedome; which is the ſterne of authority, that doth guide it in an euen and ſteady courſe, that it daſh not againſt thoſe two dangerous rockes, ſlauiſh feare on the one ſide, and contempt on the other. And the chiefe vſe of wiſedome is to carry ones ſelfe ſo, that loue and reuerence may not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiere, cut, and ſo deſtroy each the other. Its hard of an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſo familiar, to be loued and not ſlightly ſet by; harder to be reuerenced, not ſlightly feared, not hated. Prudence therefore muſt ſo manage the matter, that they may keepe theſe two affections in their due temper, free from exceſſe, free from defect, ſo doing good according to the dignity of the place. Now this wiſedome muſt bee vſed in giuing commandements and reprooſes; with which two it is fit euery wiſe man ſhould content himſelfe in this ſociety. We dare not allow him to proceede ſo farre as to correct by blowes. Indeed what Chriſtian woman will carry her ſelfe ſo, that a man of any indifferent good behauiour ſhould neede to ſtrike? Let his wiſdome rather appeare in abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from blowes, &amp; preuenting the breaking forth of ſuch enormities as may challenge them, than in giuing them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and (as he thinkes) in due manner. But for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and reproofes he may, he muſt giue them: and herein we will direct him as we are able.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Firſt, in commanding hee muſt regard theſe two rules chiefly. One is, that he doe not command ſenſeleſſe and vnreaſonable (much leſſe wicked &amp; vnlawfull) things, that are grounded meerely vpon his wilfulneſſe, and no iuſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1436:14"/>beſides. Such commandings make her take him for an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foole, not a wiſe head: and that conceit neuer riſeth but with the vtter ruine of reuerence, and ſo of his authority. The wife indeed ſhould caſt her eye onely vpon the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or vnlawfulneſſe of the thing, asking none other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but whether it offend God, yea or no: but the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band muſt conſider further, that that which hee giues in charge be diſcreete, vſefull and commodious, and whereof himſelfe can yeeld ſome ſufficient cauſe to make it appeare fit and needfull to be done. He that doth not ſo, ſhuts out his commandements, as a childe doth his arrow (a cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>height, as they ſay) not at any marke; and what is more ridiculous than ſuch childiſhneſſe in a man of yeares? Hee that bids his wife doe a thing without reaſon, doth as if it were ride without a bridle. If ſuch a mans horſe be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding gentle and well broken, he will ſure either run out of the way, or ſtumble and caſt the rider. So if ſuch a mans wife be not more then ordinary in meekenes and patience, ſhe will either rebell againſt him, or contemne him. For the good that commeth from the thing commanded, yeeldeth ſufficiency of argument to the womans vn derſtanding, whereby ſhee may controlle her tumultuous riſing of her paſſions (that will aske, Why ſhould I bee at all that paines for the mans will?) lending ayde as it were to bring them ſoone into ſubiection. Which if it bee wanting, it is hardly poſſible, but they will mutiney at the leaſt, if not breake out into open act of rebellion. Looke therefore that thou bid thy wife doe nothing, which reaſon (not onely will) doth not firſt bid thee. Againe, in commanding it muſt be regarded, that authority deſcend not vnto low, meane, and triuiall things, which are not of any moment or importance in the family. The life of the head muſt bee deriued euen vnto the feete; ſo the husbands authority doth indeed guide all, euen the meaneſt things in the family; but the head is not alwayes actually ſtooping vnto the foote; for then the body would grow crooked and ill ſhapen: ſo muſt not the husband be charging, bidding and intermedling by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1436:15"/>ſtrict commandements in the ſmall matters of the family; putting his hand (as it were) to euery matter. For that gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is much worne, muſt needes become thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare: and this power of commanding is like a veſture for high dayes, to be put on, for ſome ſpeciall and needfull oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. When the husband wilbe huſwife and all, and bee dealing with brewing, baking, waſhing, and the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of theſe and the like buſineſſes, it comes to paſſe that his wife can helpe in nothing, becauſe he will do all things. When the man will bid and charge ſo eagerly in a thing of nothing, as if his whole eſtate did depend vpon ſeruing the ſwine, or waſhing the bucke, &amp;c. this diſvalues his word, and makes his charge of no regard. In ſuch things he ſhould let his wife rule vnder him, &amp; giue her leaue to know more than himſelfe which hath greater maters and more neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning the family to exerciſe his knowledge. And if he ſee any thing in theſe and the like matters done diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, it were his part to aduiſe and counſell, rather than command. He that will be drawing out his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for euery light thing, ſhall finde it at length regarded in nothing. See then that the matter be ſo much worth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou lay a charge concerning it. And theſe be the two ſpeciall rules of wiſedome for commandements. Let thein bee concerning things vſefull and alſo weighty for the family.</p>
            <p n="20">20. The ſame vertue muſt be practiſed in the matter of reprouing; wherein, if in any thing, great warineſſe ought to bee vſed. This is a thing needfull, I meane reproofe, and if it ſpeed well, doth much good; if ill, is very dangerous: ſo that in adminiſtring it, diſcreete care muſt be had, that a man poyſon not, in ſtead of healing. Now for the prudent giuing a reproofe, three things are of needfull obſeruation: Firſt, that a man open not his mouth to tell his wife of a fault, when he perceiues himſelfe to be hot &amp; burning with violent paſſion. A man is indeed moſt ready to ſpeake then; but leaſt able to ſpeake well. If an admonition bee Vomited
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1436:15"/>forth, how can it doe good? how ſhall that proſper, which proceedeth from the meere drunkennes of wrath? No man goes to iudge of a colour with a moath in his eye: &amp; what other thing is paſſion to the iudgement? So that hee which then will become a reprouer, ſhall diſgrace himſelfe, not the fault; and make his wife contemne him, not condemne her ſelfe. For in ſuch caſe men vſe not to ſpeake what they ſhould, but what they like; nor what is moſt fitting the fault, but moſt ſutable to their diſtempers. Thus the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion is not proportioned to the offence, but as licour it ſauoureth of the caske, and is outragious, as was the heart whence it came. By which meanes in ſeeking to mend a fault in another, he commits a greater himſelfe, and makes the other worſe, not better. If thou beeſt an husband therefore, take this aduice. When there is neede of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, there is alſo neede of wiſedome to giue it. Doe it therefore when thou art in thy right wits. Paſſion is a ſhort madneſſe: can any thing bee done diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ly in that fit? When thou art quiet, when thy iudgement is cleare, when thy heart is ſetled, when thou art thy ſelfe, then ſhew thy wife her fault; elſe thou ſhalt neuer bring her to the ſight of it. Secondly, it is a point of wiſedome for the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to conſider his wiues temper alſo, and obſerue if ſhee bee fit to receiue, as well as hee to vtter wholeſome words. For when ſhee is enraged by paſſion, or deiected by griefe and ſickneſſe, which make a ready way for paſſion, it is no time to bring forth a reproofe. No man will hoyſe vp ſayle in a tempeſt; no Phyſician will adminiſter Phyſicke vpon a full ſtomacke. Thoſe words are caſt away that are vttered when paſſion hath both ſtopped vp the eares, and brought the minde out of taſte. She will not relliſh a reproofe when her heart is imbittered. Al is then taken as proceeding from ill will and hatred, though neuer ſo meant: for ſhe iudgeth with a diſtempered iudgement. At ſuch times therefore powre not forth all thy minde, but deferre it till afterwards. When thou ſeeſt a man drunken, thou firſt getteſt him to ſleepe, before thou chide him for his drunkenneſſe. Thinke
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1436:16"/>not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtrong drink is more violent then ſtrong paſſion. They both make him in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are with exceſſe, vncapable of all good counſel Say not, I will not ſuffer her to beare away the laſt word? This were to ſcold with her, a thing abſurd for a man. Better that ſhe haue the laſt word, then both mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply worſe words, till thy ſelfe alſo bee caſt into the ſame phrenſie. For it is extremely difficult to talke long with an angry man, &amp; not grow hot for company: but to contend with him, &amp; not be like him, is impoſſible. And what more vndecent and vnſightly thing then to infect thy ſelfe in ſtead of amending her? as if the Phyſician &amp; the patient ſhould fal together by the eares about taking the potion. Wherefore as thou lookeſt to haue all other things fit to receiue what thou putteſt into them, as the veſſell the liquor, the ground the ſeed, &amp;c. So look that thy wiues hart be fit to entertaine the reproofe, &amp; that there be roome for thy words; which is then when ſhe is quiet, well pleaſed &amp; pacified, not ſowred &amp; leauened with raſh anger, or much griefe. Now the third &amp; moſt neceſſary part of wiſedome is to giue a reproofe in ſecret. Euery man is moſt willing then to heare of his faults, when none is preſent to report the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe but himſelfe. We are all naturally iealous of our credit; women are ſo princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally; &amp; if they take a thing as done in way of diſgrace, they are prouoked to doe worſe, not induced to amend. So that it is a matter and loue equally, to ſee that none eare be priuy to the fault reproued, but her owne. Men that lay plaſters to ſores, chuſe a chamber, not the market place; they loue not to doe ſuch things with a witneſſe. Chriſt bids reproue thy neighbour;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.5.</note> firſt betwixt him and thee; then take two more with thee, and ſo proceede further. More loue is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to a wife, and ſo more ſecrecie. But ſay ſhee offend in publique before the ſeruants, children, ſtrangers. Then ſhew thy diſlike in a patient manner of ſpeaking, that al may ſee thou winkeſt not at the fault, and be much in expreſſing griefe rather then anger. Leaue the lawfull ſharpneſſe and wholeſome launcing (as I may terme it) for a reproofe till you come alone. By that time ſhee will ſhame to remember how ſhe ouer-ſhot herſelfe, if thou giue her not aduantage
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1436:16"/>of replying, by committing the like abſurdity at the ſame time. Neither feare that faults ſo healed in ſecrecy ſhould infect the children &amp; ſeruants. Nay thy preſent griefe &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like wil worke more vpon them then any reproofe; &amp; there is time in her abſence to warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo offending, in theirs euen to chide her for giuing ſo bad an example. They may know thou haſt reproued, though they heare thee not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can in no ſort allow the fooliſh raſhnes of thoſe husbands (yea wee moſt ſharply condemne it) w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> muſt needs out with their reproofe before children, ſeruants, and perhaps alſo ſtrangers (as if their ſtomack were ſurcharged with it) not hauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wit to refrain til the oporrunity of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatnes. Theſe men diſgrace themſelues in diſcrediting their wiues, as the head gaines the knocke if the heeles be taken vp. For now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife conceiues that her diſgrace is aymed at: hence ſhe becomes more cholericke, perhaps alſo to iuſtifie the matter, that prouokes him to more anger, kindles more heat; &amp; ſo in concluſion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> growes to a plain braule or fray, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſhould haue bin a kind &amp; Chriſtian reproofe. Had not theſe bin better well ſaued till another time, then ſo dangerouſly miſſpent at this time to both their hurts, both their diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? And this is the practiſe of wiſedome.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The next vertue is mildnes. This ſociety comes nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to equality, &amp; therefore allowes familiarity (w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> muſt not be ſuffred in other couplings of ſuperiors &amp; inferiors) &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more gentlenes. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweet ſauce of this gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> makes it not to ſeem ouer tart, it is the ſoft lining of this yoke of authority, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> without it, is vnſupportable. No woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can endure gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if gentlenes do not temper it.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Now this gentlenes muſt be vſed in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements and reproofes. In commandements, both for the matter of them, and for the manner, For the matter of them it muſt bee regarded, that a man extend not his commanding power (in the vſe thereof) too farre; neither ſhew himſelfe rigorous in euery thing, but bee content to gratifie his wife in ſome things, that ſhee may leſſe vnwillingly, yea with more cheerefulneſſe bee ſubiect in other things. Obedience would be inticed and allured, and as it were by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1436:17"/>committing it to it owne diſpoſing in matters of inferiour nature, that it may follow more dutifully, when more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity requires more ſpeedy and voluntary obſequiouſneſſe. The Sunamite is a noble paterne for this matter.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.22</note> His wife in the middeſt of harueſt (he not knowing any cauſe) requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a man and two aſſes from that needful and haſty worke, to attend her vnto the Prophet. He is not vrgent in asking the cauſe, nor peremptory in repelling the ſuite, but grants her deſire, though it might ſeeme ſomething inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. He knew her to bee no gadder, and one day was not much. Thus ſhee had liberty to depart; and hee himſelfe was a gayner by it, as being freed from a great deale of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which the newes of his ſonnes death would haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured; and obteyning vnſpeakable comfort in his reuiuing: for ſhe ſaw him rayſed vp, before hee knew of his diſeaſe. It was in <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo more than ordinary gentleneſſe, that in a matter ſo neerly concerning him, would condeſcend to his wiues paſſionate requeſt, about her mayde <hi>Hagar.</hi> Let not the husband bee as churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> to his wife, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe paternes of husbandly mildneſſe, which will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get at once both loue and reuerence, teſtifying kindneſſe, and procuring it. Hee that will bee Lord in euery thing, ſtretcheth the authority of his ſtring ſo high, that it is at leaſt in danger of breaking. So carry thy ſelfe to thy wife, that ſhe may perceiue herſelfe to haue entred, not into ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile thraldome, but louing ſubiection.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Then when neede requireth a commandement to be giuen, it muſt be, for the manner, not imperious, not in the heate and extremity of inforcing and charging words; but with a ſweet inſtinct of kindeneſſe (as the head doth moue the members of the body) by louing perſwaſions and familiar requeſts. Indeed if the wife try the maſtery, and caſt off the yoke of obedience, ſuch her diſtemper makes it not alone lawfull, but very meere, that the husband (with good words and behauiour, not bitter, not raging) doe ſtand for his authority euen ſtifly and peremptorily, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1436:17"/>that he will haue his will in things lawfull. But ſuch a courſe would be ſeldome vſed, and that alone in matters of ſome importance, that are worth ſo much earneſtneſſe. It is more ſafe, and as honourable ſubduing a rebellious City by treaties of peace with good and fauorable conditions, than by the battery of ordinance, and fierce dint of the ſword. So that husband doth with moſt praiſe and happines ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due his wiues paſſions of diſobedience, that can effect it by faire meanes. Yea indeed ſhe muſt be a monſtrous and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>womanly woman, that being drawne by entreatie will not yeeld. Authority is like the arts of Logick and Rhetoricke, that muſt in ſpeaking be vſed, and yet concealed: and then they moſt preuaile when being vſed, they are leaſt ſeene. It preuents reſiſting, to requeſt when thou mayſt charge. There is nothing to ſtriue for, when a man doth not, as it were vaunt his ſuperiority. Things are alſo beſt done when the will is allured, rather than the body compelled. If thou ſtand vpon it, and come with flat commandements (as, <hi>you ſhall;</hi> and, <hi>I will make you;</hi> and, <hi>you were as good as you did;</hi> and, <hi>you ſhall know that I am maſter, &amp;c.</hi> and the like big words,) the heart goes againſt that which the hand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes; and thou art diſliked inwardly, though perhaps o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed in ſhew: and if obedience come not from the heart, can it laſt long? This is the way to preuaile with leaſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the inferiour, &amp; toyle to the ſuperiour, if with milde words hee wiſh this and this, rather then with imperious ſpeeches enioyne it. Men that ride horſes haue a wand and a ſpurre, both; they wil rather ſet forward their horſes with the whisk &amp; ſound, or perhaps little touch of the ſmal ſtick, then with the ſharpneſſe of their iron ſpurre. They proceed not to ſpurring till their horſe be either reſtie or tiry; and if tiry, that doth more hurt. So the husband ſhould gouerne his wife, &amp; prouoke her to accompliſh his will with quiet, pleaſing and inſinuating termes, rather than open and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, much leſſe violent commandings, vnleſſe ſhee bee more then ordinarily vnruly. Chriſt beſeecheth his Church moſt an end, which hee might with moſt right command.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1436:18"/>Let the husband imitate that beſt husband, and beware of, <hi>Doe it, or you had beſt;</hi> and, <hi>You ſhall whether you will or no; I will haue it ſo to croſſe you, &amp;c.</hi> Such an husband will croſſe himſelfe moſt. Violent things are neuer of long continuance. And this is mildneſſe in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p n="24">24. It muſt bee vſed in reprouing, where it is rather more neceſſary, by how much bitterneſſe is leſſe to bee brooked, and a reproofe leſſe eaſie to bee borne. And this muſt alſo be ſhewed in the matter, and in the manner of a reproofe. For the matter, in not finding fault for euery trifle that he ſees amiſſe, nor chiding for euery infirmity. Many things muſt be paſſed by (yea all things that be not ſomewhat groſſe, and would endanger the wiues ſelfe, if ſhe ſhould not heare of them roundly) with none or halfe a word. This effect of loue is very needfull towards ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that it paſſeth by wants and weakeneſſes; much more in the houſhold, and in the neareſt couple of the houſhold. Charity is in this ſenſe a great couer-fault; it will ſee none but where they be; and many it will ſee and not ſee, and not ſpeake of, and it deſcends to a reproofe with a willing vnwillingneſſe. This vertue ſhould abound in this ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Heere Chriſts example muſt bee followed of all huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. He ſhuts his eyes as it were, and will not ſpy out all his Churches faults; hee will not marke extremely what is done amiſſe; he knowes ſhe is but duſt, and is aſſured that ſhe cannot but offend in many things: Yet hee puts it vp, and not ſo much as checkes her, vnleſſe ſhe comes to ſome wilfulnes in ſinning. Let all that be husbands doe likewiſe: conſider you be matched with women, the weaker veſſels: thinke how many faults your ſelues haue; and if they haue ſome, wonder not that they be ſo many, but that not more; and with ſilence, ſo much as is poſſible; and when it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be ſilent (viz. in weakeneſſes and infirmities) ſtriue to amend them. It is a great deale ſafer heere to bee defectiue than to exceed; to be ſomewhat purblinde, than too Eagle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1436:18"/>In this inwardnes of conuerſation, it is impoſſible but diuers wants ſhall offer themſelues to be ſeene: and he that will prye for them, and take occaſion vpon euery ſlight matter, to draw forth his reproofe, ſhal himſelfe liue in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall diſcontentment, &amp; yeeld but little quiet to his wife. For from hence ſhee will conceiue, (and that not without ſome cauſe) that he loues her not much; and this will cauſe their affections to warpe and chap, till all be full of diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Be not extreme heere, be not rigorous; but as a mothers tendernes of loue makes her not reſpect or obſerue many deformities in her owne childe; ſo ſtand thou affected to thine owne wife. Pray to God againſt all her faults, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto her all vertues; reproue not leſſer wants &amp; natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral weakneſſes: let her perceiue cloſely that thou knoweſt, but art not willing to take notice of them, that ſhe may take the more diligent notice thereof herſelfe, and be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to reforme them.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Moreouer for the manner of reprouing, when the thing is moſt needfull, it muſt yet be gentle. The words and behauiour vſed to declare and preſſe the fault vpon her, muſt be milde, and ſuch as breathe forth loue &amp; pity. A reproofe muſt be applied as a plaſter, not with rating, but with moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rather. It cannot be auoided, no not in the beſt, but this medicine wilbe needed: yet the husband muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, not to vſe more roughnes than is fit to his owne fleſh. Reproofe of it ſelfe, as it were a potion goes againſt the ſtomack: we neede not by our bitternes make it more lothſome, as it were by a foule &amp; vnſightly cup. The mothers care muſt be ſhewed heere. She giues the childe worme-ſeede to kill the wormes, and raiſins to till downe the worme-ſeed: ſo muſt a man reprehend to reproue the fault, and yet with great lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingnes of ſpeech and countenance, to ſweeten the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. No patient was neuer yet ſo ſicke and deſirous of health, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could be perſwaded to drinke a potion ſcalding hot: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which burnes the lips would neuer finde admittance into the ſtomack, though it were the moſt wholſome drink.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1436:19"/>It is iuſt ſo with a reproofe: if it ſcalde the eare, as I may ſo ſpeake, with vpbraiding and diſgracefull ſpeeches, with bitter taunts, ſcoffes and mocks, with vilifying and rayling words, with a fierie looke, and aſ arkling eye, with a raging exaltation of the voyce and demeanure of the body, it will neuer gaine paſſage to the hart. Compaſſion, loue, kindnes, declaration of ones ſorrow for the fault, deſire of their good, and will of their amendment, theſe be the things that frame the will to accept an admonition, and do much helpe the kindly working of it. I am not againſt the wholeſome earneſtneſſe of reprouing, and that ſharpnes which in ſome caſes God commands; this may ſtand without bitterneſſe, without violence of words and geſture, without that fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt which we ſpeake. A thing need not to be key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold, though it ſcalde not; there is a large difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two. Then an admonition is healthfully ſharpe and earneſt, when a man in plainneſſe &amp; with good termes layes open the abſurdity, naughtineſſe and danger of the ſinne, enforcing theſe conſiderations vpon the heart and conſcience of the party, euen ſomewhat lamentably, and with ſome mouing, but ſtill with declaration of ſorrow more then anger: and this ought to bee done. In one word therefore let thy reproofes bee warme, not hot. And thus much for the practiſe of mildnes.</p>
            <p n="26">26. The third vertue to bee ſhewed by the husband, is Iuſtice, the ſoule of gouernment, the true temperature of authority, without which it rots and putrifieth, and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates into the moſt fulſome and ſtinking carrion of tyranny. Now the husband muſt deale iuſtly with his wife in foure things: Firſt, in allowing her ſufficient maintenance, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his place and ability, and that willingly, and with a liberall hand. Hee muſt not thinke himſelfe ſo abſolutely Lord of all, but that ſhee muſt alſo haue the free and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of all, according as his calling requires, and his ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency will beare. Indeed if ſhe ſhould exceede both, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, his authority muſt ſound retraite vnto her
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1436:19"/>lauiſhneſſe; neither muſt he weaken, much leſſe ouerthrow his eſtate by pranking her body, and feeding her tooth: this were after a ſort to kill himſelfe, her, his children, and whole family, with fondneſſe towards her, a part full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe. But let her be made equall partner of that which her husband hath. So be it ſhe cut her coate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her cloath, Iuſtice will not permit that ſhe ſhould be ſcanted with niggardice, which is ſo neere a companion. The husband muſt communicate maintenance to the wife, as the head doth animal ſpirits to the body, plentifully, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly: for if any ſtoppance grow in this conueyance, great diſtempers muſt of neceſſity inſue: yea, not alone whileſt himſelfe liueth, but euen after his deceaſe alſo: and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to leaue the world, muſt he prouide, after his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that her eſtate be competent, and that ſhee be not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to her children, and forced to ſtand beholding vnto them, ouer whom ſhee ſhould command. And this is one point of Iuſtice. Another, and the ſecond is, that the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band compell not his wife by his authority to attempt things vnlawfull. Where God hath commanded, let not him forbid; where God hath forbidden, let not him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. What a madnes is it to force either to diſobey God, or him? Will he exceede his commiſſion, and thinke to be yeelded vnto? Is not this vnrighteous in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, for the Deputie to take vpon him euen againſt the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lord? This is to iuſtle her into ſome ſtinking guzzle or ditch: whence it muſt follow, that if ſhee proue ſtronger than himſelfe, and will not be thruſt in, yet he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders himſelfe odious that attempted to do her harme: if ſhe proue weake, and fall in, he muſt be at the paines to pull her (out) and make her cleane againe: otherwiſe both muſt periſh; the one for ſinning, the other for driuing vnto ſin. Wherefore in ſome doing he violates both Iuſtice &amp; Wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhewing himſelfe in one action, both a foole before her, and a rebell againſt God. Nay, he muſt not alone ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from vrging her vnto things that indeed are, but vnto ſuch alſo, as ſhee vpon ſome ſuppoſed reaſon, grounded on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1436:20"/>the Word of God, thinkes to be vnlawfull. The conſcience is Gods immediate officer, and commanding by vertue of its commiſſion, which is Gods reuealed wil; though it erre in conſtruction of that commiſſion, yet muſt it be obeyed, and ouer-weigh the authority of all other commanders, till it be ſatisfied and ſet downe with reaſons, manifeſting ſuch miſtaking: for whoſoeuer goes againſt conſcience in things thought to be ſinfull, and are not, will at length offend againſt it in ſuch things as both are, and are thought to be faults. Indeed if ſhee will pretend conſcience, and cannot alleage a reaſon out of the Word of God, yet may carry ſome ſhew, this is obſunacy; and in ſuch caſe the thing being of waight and vſe, it is ſafe, yea needfull, if rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perſwade not, to compell her. But when ſhee grounds vpon the Word of God, though miſ-interpreted and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, ſhe muſt be reſolued, and not compelled. Not euery ſcruple of conſcience makes a thing ſin to a man, but that which is grounded vpon Gods Word, by which alone-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt bee informed and guided: which when it is, though it bee miſ-informed through want of iudgement, yet it retaines its owne authority; and then to enforce the wife againſt it, were to force her to ſinne, the moſt vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous thing that can bee in a Gouernour. None is Lord, but onely the Lord of Heauen and earth. Bee not therefore ſo vnrighteous towards thy wife, as to vrge her either to diſpleaſe GOD, or her conſcience, leaning on his word. The third part of Iuſtice, is, not to reproue without a fault, nor ſharply for a leſſer fault: The former of theſe is to lay a plaſter on a found place, which is a needleſſe labour at all times, and often dangerous: for it may cauſe a ſore. So to finde fault without a cauſe, may procure a fault. The latter is to ſeare, and cut and cauterize, where a Lenitiue would ſerue; and to giue a violent ſtrong purgation, where an eaſie pill would ſuffice for health. This comes from cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and breedes diſtemper. A reproofe muſt come forth, not when a man is angred, but when God is offended: not when our profit or pleaſure is croſſed, but when Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1436:20"/>is broken. And as the plaſter muſt bee fitted to the wound, the medicine to the diſeaſe; ſo the admonition to the fault. For of thoſe ſinnes which neceſſarily call for an admonition, there are degrees, according to the increaſe whereof, a man ſhould ſhew more or leſſe anger and diſlike. So that the husband muſt bee more earneſt in reprouing, not when ſhee hath committed a ſmaller ſinne againſt GOD, that turneth more to his loſſe; but when ſhee hath done a greater euill againſt GOD, though hee bee a ſmall, yea, no loſer; yea a gainer by it for his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profit. And alwayes when the fault is amended, ceaſe vpbraiding: this is a moſt vnequall thing. When the fire is thorowly quenched, who would ſtand caſting on water? Now the laſt point of Iuſtice followes, which is, that a man endeauour to confirme and increaſe the good things that are in his wife, by all good incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and teſtification of his loue and good liking, aſ-well as to reforme and diminiſh the euill things by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. Wee prouender an horſe as well as whip and ſpurre him, elſe the beſt would tyre: and the wife muſt bee animated to good things, and not onely withdrawne from euill. A man ſhould vſe his right eye as well as his left. Nothing can bee more baſe then to bee a fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpier, a fly-blower, that is, alwayes nibling where the skinne is off. Fie vpon that husband, which like a flye ſeekes euer for a galled place to blow his maggots on; this healeth not, but pricks, and makes all things worſe. It is a great vnrighteouſnes to looke onely to the worſt things. Iuſtice giues one his due for well and ill both; which not to doe is the bane of loue, on both ſides cauſing iarres, heart-burnings, ſecret diſlike, and open contention at the laſt. Therefore if euer thou will liue with comfort, conſider as well what vertues thy wife hath, as what vices; what good, as what bad; &amp; what help and benefit thou haſt by her, as what hindrance; to comfort &amp; ſtrengthen her in the one, as help her out of the other: yea &amp; let her ſee that thou takeſt notice rather of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt things.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1436:21"/>Surely theſe good herbes will grow beſt &amp; ſafeſt in the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine. And thus much for the mans duty: wherein I haue bene more long, becauſe diſorders in him are more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and hurtfull, as diſeaſes in the head; and any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in the great wheele of a clocke.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Now proceede we to the womens duty, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the men leaue to chew the cud awhile, requeſt the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to liſten with more diligence than before. The whole duty of the wife is referred to two heads. The firſt is, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her inferiority: the next, to carry her ſelfe as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour. Firſt then the wiues iudgement muſt be conuinced, that ſhe is not her husbands equall, yea that her husband is her better by farre; elſe there can bee no contentment, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in her heart, or in her houſe. If ſhee ſtand vpon termes of equality, much more of being better than he is, the very root of good carriage is withered, and the fountaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of dryed vp. Out of place, out of peace. And woe to theſe miſerable aſpiring ſhoulders, that content not themſelues to take their roome, next below the head. If euer thou pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be a good wife, and to liue comfortably, ſet downe this with thy ſelfe. <hi>Mine husband is my ſuperiour, my better;</hi> he hath authority and rule ouer mee: Nature hath giuen it him, hauing framed our bodies to tendernes, mens to more hardneſſe. God hath giuen it him, ſaying to our firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Euah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Thy deſire ſhalbe ſubiect to him, and hee ſhall rule ouer thee.</hi> His will is the tye and tedder euen of my deſires and wiſhes. I will not ſtriue againſt GOD and nature. Though my ſinne hath made my place tedious, yet I will confeſſe the truth, <hi>Mine husband is my ſuperiour, my better.</hi> If the wife doe not learne this leſſon perfectly, if ſhe haue it not without booke, euen at her fingers ends, as we ſpeake, if her very heart condeſcend not to it, there will bee wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, repining, ſtriuing, viyng to be equall with him, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue him; and thus their life wilbe but a battell, and a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of maſteries. A wofull liuing.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1436:21"/>
            <p n="28">28. Secondly, the wife being reſolued that her place is the lower, muſt carry herſelfe as an inferiour. It little bootes to confeſſe his authority in word, if ſhee frame not to ſubmiſſion indeede. Now ſhee ſhall teſtifie her inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in a Chriſtian manner, by practiſing thoſe two vertues of reuerence and obedience, which are appropriate to the place of inferiours.</p>
            <p n="29">29. And firſt for reuerence, the wife owes as much of that to her husband, as the children or the ſeruants doe to her, yea, as they doe to him: onely it is allowed that it bee ſweetned with more loue and more familiarity. The wife ſhould not thinke ſo erroniouſly of her place, as if ſhe were not bound equally with the children and ſeruants to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence her husband; all inferiours owe reuerence alike. The difference is onely this, ſhe may be more familiar, not more rude then they, as being more deare, not leſſe ſubiect to him.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Alſo this reuerence of hers muſt bee both inward and outward. Firſt, her heart muſt bee kept inwardly, in a dutifull reſpect of him, and ſhee muſt regard him as Gods Deputy, not looking to his perſon but his place; nor think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much who and what an one hee is, as whoſe officer. This the Apoſtle doth very ſtrictly inioyne, ſaying, <hi>Let the wife ſee that ſhee feare her husband.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ</hi> 5. laſt verſe.</note> As if hee had ſaid: Of all things let her moſt carefully labour not to faile in this duty: for if ſhee doe, her whole life beſides will bee rude and vnbeſeeming. And you muſt know that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle meanes heere not a ſlauiſh, but a louing feare, ſuch as may well ſtand with the neareſt vnion of hearts, as between Chriſt and his Church. And this feare is when, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his place, ſhee doth abhorre it as the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, next to the breach of Gods Commandement, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe and offend her husband. Men ſtand in right awe of God, when they loath it as the greateſt of al euils, to breake his Commandement and grieue his Spirit; and the wife
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1436:22"/>feares her husband in good manner, when ſhe doth ſhunne it as the next euill, to diſpleaſe, grieue and diſobey her husband, who is next to GOD aboue her in the family. Such regard her heart muſt haue of her head, that it keepe hand and tongue and all from diſorder. I know this is not cuſtomable, nay it is ſcarce thought ſeemely amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny women; nay they are as little for their husbands, as they for them; yea they deſpiſe him, yea they haue inuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this precept, and cauſe their husbands to feare them. This impudencie, this vnwomanhood tracks the way to the harlots houſe, and giues all wiſe men to know, that ſuch haue, or would, or ſoone will caſt off the care of honeſty, as of loyaltie. But if thou wilt bee a vertuous wife, deale with thine heart to make it ſtand in awe of thine husband: and know that God hath not for nought giuen the former <hi>Caueat</hi> to women. As thou groweſt in this inward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſo looke to get the better of all other infirmities: as thou art careleſſe herein, ſo ſhalt thou bee peſtered with all other enormities. Where the heart ſets light by any one, the words and geſtures wilbe contemptuous. If the fountaine be muddy with neglect, ſo ſhall the ſtreames.</p>
            <p n="31">31. And as the heart principally, ſo next the outward behauiour muſt be regarded in three ſpeciall things. Firſt, in ſpeeches and geſtures vnto him. Theſe muſt carry the ſtamp of feare vpon them, and not be cutted, ſharpe, ſullen, paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, teechie, but meeke, quiet, ſubmiſſiue, which may ſhew that ſhe conſiders who herſelfe is, and to whom ſhe ſpeakes. The wiues tongue towards her husband muſt bee neither keene, nor looſe, her countenance neither ſwelling nor deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: her behaurour not flinging, not puffing, not diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented; but ſauouring of all lowlineſſe and quietneſſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Looke what kinde of words or behauiour thou wouldſt diſlike from thy ſeruant or childe, thoſe muſt thou not giue to thine husband: for thou art equally comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſubiect. Herein <hi>Sarah</hi> once faulted, ſhe was aloft in the boughes; <hi>God be Iudge betweene me and thee.</hi> Heerein
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1436:22"/>alſo <hi>Rachel</hi> offended, that in a pelting chaſe came ſuming, and chod with her husband; <hi>Giue me children, or I die. Iacob</hi> could not brooke this without anger, though he loued her tenderly. Herein <hi>Micol</hi> alſo was out of the way, when ſhe came ſcoffing and flouting to her husband <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>How glorious was the King of Iſrael to day, &amp;c.</hi> when her husband in her conceite (though not indeed) carried himſelfe ſomewhat vnfit for a Kings place; ſhee cannot admoniſh him in good ſort, but with bitter taunting breakes a ieſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Theſe examples ſhew how ſubiect women are to diſreuerent behauiour; and withall how lothſome, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>womanly they bee. Yet for all theſe warnings wee haue ſome women that can chaſe and ſcold with their husbands, and raile vpon them, and reuile them, and ſhake them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuch termes and carriage, as were vnſufferable towards a ſeruant. Staines of woman-kinde, blemiſhes of their ſexe, monſters in natures, botches of humane ſociety, rude, graceleſſe, impudent, next to harlots, if not the ſame with them. Let ſuch words leaue a bliſter behinde them, and let the canker eate out theſe tongues. But beſides theſe ſo notorious ones, euen women otherwiſe vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, muſt ſee their faults in this behalfe. They can take vp their husbands with quicke ſpeeches ſharpely ſet on. They can ſet them downe ſhort, with a cutted anſwer, with a frowning countenance, with a diſdainfull looke, and the ſide turned towards them in diſpleaſure. Why wilt thou teach thy children to bee rebellious, and ſhew thy ſeruants how to ſwell, pout, and fume? Thinkeſt thou ſuch behauiour will not infect? Shall not they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vſe it to thee? or is it leſſe tollerable in thee? Bee ſubmiſſiue rather, and let them learne reuerence from thee to practiſe to thee. That woman makes her ſelfe vile, that ſets her husband at nought, or elſe ſeemes to doe it.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Secondly, the wife muſt expreſſe reuerence towards her husband in her ſpeeches and geſtures before him and in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1436:23"/>his preſence to others. His company muſt make her more reſpectiue how ſhee carries herſelfe towards any elſe. Her words muſt not be loud and ſnappiſh to the children, to the ſeruants in his ſight. If ſhee perceiue a fault, yet muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that her better ſtands by, and not ſpeake without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; and then vtter that in more ſtill and milde manner, which in his abſence ſhee may ſet on with more roundnes. No woman of gouernment will allow her children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to bee loud and brawling before her; and ſhall ſhee before her husband bee ſo herſelfe? What is become of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority then? Yea her reuerence doth inioyne her ſilence when ſhee ſtands by. I meane not vtter abſtinence from ſpeech, but vſing few words, and thoſe low and milde, not eagre,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.11.</note> not loud. <hi>Paul</hi> commands the women to <hi>learne in ſilence.</hi> The word is, <hi>in quietneſſe:</hi> wherein be not alone inioynes a publicke, but euen a generall ſilence to hold in the houſe and other like meetings: for why ſhould that bee reſtrained without any neede, which doth well receiue a larger extent? The reaſon of which duty is grounded euen vpon the conſideration of the two ſexes: for euen as youth is inferiour to age, and the yong folke to the aged (vnleſſe ſome other reſpect doe ouer-ballance this difference, as ſometimes it falles out that the younger is in authority, and the elder vnder it; the younger hath more excellent gifts; the elder fewer, and ſuch like; by which the inferiority of young men is ſhadowed, and as it were coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:) ſo is the male ſexe preferred before the female in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of place &amp; dignity, as all men will yeeld that read what the Scriptures ſpeake in that behalfe. Now if there bee an inferiority of the ſexe, by what thing ſhould it bee better expreſſed, rather then this, by which alſo younger people muſt teſtifie theirs, namely, to ſpeake little and low before them? For what leſſe thing can bee required in witneſſe of this difference? Let women then either excuſe chat and loudneſſe in young folkes before their ancients, in children and ſeruants before them; or elſe condemne it in themſelues before their husbands, yea before any men. I know this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1436:23"/>duty goes againſt the haire: for where there is ſuddenneſſe of wit, and ſcarcity of wiſedome (as in the moſt of this ſexe comparatiuely) there is readines to ſpeake, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of words; but amongſt all wiſe-men, talakatiuenes of women (chiefly when it comes to loud and earneſt words) hath bene reputed a fault moſt of all in the husbands pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Now then let women learne ſilence, and let the reuerent account of their husbands worke in them a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all moderation of ſpeech whileſt they bee in place.</p>
            <p n="33">33. Thirdly, the womans ſpeeches of the husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde his backe, muſt bee dutifull and reſpectiue. Shee muſt not call him by light names, nor talke of him with any kinde of careleſneſſe and ſlightnes of ſpeech, much leſſe with deſpitefull and reprochfull termes. Heerein the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fact of <hi>Sarah,</hi> commended to our imitation, muſt be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in practice. When ſhee thought of her husband in the abſence of all company, ſhee intituled him by the name of <hi>my Lord.</hi> If in her priuate conceit ſhee gaue him ſo good and honourable titles, what would ſhe haue done in company? what in his owne preſence? what vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? So the women muſt inure themſelues to ſubmiſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoughts and ſpeeches in their husbands abſence, that they may the better practiſe the ſame in their preſence: for cuſtome in this thing hath great force. Who would brooke a childe ſpeaking diſgracefully and murmuring. of his father behinde his backe? And ſhall it be ſuffered in a wife? By how much heere is more certaine tryall of her her inward affection &amp; diſpoſition, by ſo much muſt ſhe be more attentiue to her words in ſuch caſe. Very dread may make a woman giue good words before her husbands face, becauſe ſhe dares do no other, and he will brooke none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but this ſhewes a conſcionable ſubiection, when ſhe will not thinke nor ſpeake of him, though hee be farre from hearing, without ſome note of good regard, that thoſe which heare may perceiue ſhee doth account of him as her Gouernour and her better. He that allowes not an euill
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1436:24"/>thought of the Prince, will not allow euill ſpeeches of the husband in priuate talke betweene neighbours: for hee is the houſhold Prince, the domeſticall King; Though thinke husband bee from thee, let thy feare of him bee with thee, that in mentioning him to others thou ſhew not contempt. And for Reuerence thus much.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Obedience followes: as concerning which duty a plaine text auers it to the full, ſaying; <hi>Let the Wife bee ſubiect to her husband in all things, in the Lord.</hi> What need wee further proofe? Why is ſhee his wife, if ſhee will not obey? and how can ſhee require obedience of the children and ſeruants, if ſhee will not yeeld to the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? doth not ſhee exact it in his name, and as his deputie? But the thing will not bee ſo much queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as the meaſure: Not whether ſhee muſt obey, but how farre. Wherefore wee muſt extend it as farre as the Apoſtle, to a generality of things, to all things, ſo it bee in the Lord. In whatſoeuer thing obeying of him doth not diſobey God, ſhee muſt obey: and if not in all things, it were as good in nothing. It is a thankeleſſe ſeruice, if not generall. To yeeld alone in things that pleaſe her ſelfe, is not to obey him, but her owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The tryall of obedience is, when it croſſeth her deſires. To doe that which hee biddes, when ſhee would haue done without his bidding, what praiſe is it? But this declares conſcionable ſubmiſſion, when ſhee chuſeth to doe what her-ſelfe would not, becauſe her husbands wils it. And ſeeing ſhee requireth the like largeneſſe of duty in his name from the ſeruants, her-ſelfe ſhall bee Iudge againſt her-ſelfe, if ſhee giue not what ſhee lookes to receiue. But if ſufficeth not that her obedience reach to all things that are lawfull, vnleſſe it bee alſo wiling, ready, without brawling, contending, thwarting, ſowreneſſe. A good worke may bee marred in the manner of doing. And as good ſtuffe is ſpilt by bad making, ſo doth the wife diſgrace and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1436:24"/>diſfigure her obedience if ſhee hang off and contend, and bee impatient, and will not, till ſhee cannot chuſe. <hi>Needes muſt, needes ſhall,</hi> wee ſay in the Prouerbe. Such kinde of yeelding declares no reuerence, deſerues no praiſe. Then it is laudable, commendable, a note of a vertuous woman, a dutifull wiſe, when ſhee ſubmits her-ſelfe with quietneſſe, cheerefully, euen as a wel-bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken horſe turnes at the leaſt turning, ſtands at the leaſt check of the riders bridle, readily going and ſtanding as he wiſhes that fits vpon his backe. If you will haue your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience worth any thing, make no tumult about it outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, allow none within.</p>
            <p n="35">35. And for the leſſe principall duties of husband and wife concerning their ordinary ſociety, thus much. I come now to ſuch as concerne the marriage-bed, which are as needfull to bee knowne as the former, becauſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in that kinde are more capitall and dangerous, though not ſo publique. Their matrimoniall meetings muſt haue theſe three properties. Firſt, it muſt be cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: they muſt louingly, willingly and familiarly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate themſelues vnto themſelues, which is the beſt means to continue and nouriſh their mutuall naturall loue, and by which the true and proper ends of matrimony ſhall bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in beſt manner: for the husband is not his owne, but the wifes, and the wife the husbands. Secondly, their meeting muſt bee ſanctified. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, meate, drinke and marriage are good, being ſanctified by prayer. Men and women muſt not come together as brute creatures and vnreaſonable beaſts, through the heate of deſire; but muſt ſee their Maker in that his ordinance, and craue his bleſſing ſolemnely as at meales, (the Apoſtle ſpeakes of both alike) that marriage may indeede bee bleſſed vnto them. To ſanctifie the marriage-bed, and vſe it reuerently with prayer and thankſ-giuing, will make it moderate, and keepe them from growing wearie each of other (as in many it falls out,) and cauſe that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1436:25"/>luſt ſhall bee aſſwaged, which elſe ſhall bee increaſed by theſe meetings. Propagation and chaſtity, the two chiefe ends of marriage, are beſt attained by prayer and thankſ-giuing in the vſe thereof, without which they will hardly come, or not with comfort. Neither is it more then needs, to ſee God in that which ſo nearely toucheth our ſelues, as the hope of poſterity: him, as the increaſe of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Let Chriſtians therefore know the fruite of prayer euen in all things. Thirdly, their nuptiall meetings muſt bee ſeaſonable, and at lawfull times. There is a ſeaſon when God and Nature ſeioynes man and wife in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. The woman is made to be fruitfull; and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo more moiſt and cold of conſtitution. Hence it is that their naturall heate ſerues not to turne all their ſuſtenance into their owne nouriſhment; but a quantity redounding is ſet apart in a conuenient place to cheariſh and nouriſh the conception, when they ſhall conceiue. Now this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant humour (called their flowers or termes) hath (if no conception bee) it monethly iſſue or euacuation, (and in ſome oftner) vnleſſe there bee extraordinary ſtoppings and obſtructions, laſting for ſixe or ſeuen dayes in the moſt: Sometimes alſo this iſſue, through weakenes and infirmitie of nature, doth continue many more dayes. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes after child-birth there is a larger and longer empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe of the former retention, which continueth commonly for foure, fiue or ſixe weekes, &amp; in ſome longer. Now in all theſe three times and occaſions, it is ſimply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for a man to company with his own wife. The Lord telles vs ſo, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 19.25. <hi>ver.</hi> alſo <hi>chap.</hi> 18 <hi>ver.</hi> 19. alſo <hi>chap.</hi> 20. <hi>ver.</hi> 18. Of which places it is needfull, that married people ſhould take notice: to which I ſend them. Neither let women thinke themſelues diſgraced, becauſe I haue laid this matter open in plaine, but modeſt ſpeeches. Where God threatens death to the offender, can the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter bee faithfull, if he doe not plainely declare the offence? This fault is by GOD condemned to the puniſhment of death, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20.18. Beare then with neceſſary plainneſſe.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1436:25"/>And let no woman grieue that the cauſe of her fruitfulnes is knowne, when ſhee reioyceth to bee found fruitfull. Say not, that I may let them reade it. What if they cannot? what if they will not? Can the Miniſter ſo diſcharge his office, of giuing men warning that they ſinne not, becauſe they may reade it? But if any through niceneſſe or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, doe take ſnuffe at this openneſſe (for immodeſt and obſcene ſpeech they haue heard none,) they ſhall argue themſelues guilty of the ſinne, which they would not haue knowne; and ſhew rather a willingnes to commit euill, then proue it euill to teach that plainely which God hath plainely reuealed to be knowne. In a word, we muſt ſpeake all the truth, you ſhould with willingnes heare all; if not, you muſt againſt your will. Though men will be offended, wee muſt not conceale what God will haue knowne. And thus you haue heard the duties of married people, principal, and leſſe principall, for their common ſociety both mutuall and ſpeciall; and for their nuptiall ſociety in the marriage-bed. Now though I haue bene long, I will tarry to make ſome vſe and application.</p>
            <p n="36">36. And firſt, this miniſters a good inſtruction to young and vnmarried people, that they doe not vnaduiſedly ruſh into this eſtate. A thing of ſuch difficulty ſhould not bee lightly vndertaken. They ſhall haue their hands full of duty, if they get not their hearts full of grace, and their heads full of wiſedome; they ſhall finde an houſe full of trouble, and a life full of woe, meeting with gall in ſtead of hony, and grauell in ſtead of nouriſhing morſels. Wouldſt thou be married? See what wiſedome, what patience, what grace fit to gouerne or fit to obey thou findeſt in thy ſelfe. Get theſe againſt thou come to vſe them, or elſe marriage will not yeeld thee ſuch contentment, as thine imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſeth. Vaine youths grow wanton and fall in luſt, and muſt marry before they haue any power to practiſe, any vnderſtanding to know their duties; ſo they trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and diſcredit their eſtate both at once. He that leapes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1436:26"/>ouer a broad ditch with a ſhort ſtaffe, ſhall fall into the midſt; and hee that enters vpon matrimony without care to attaine great grace, ſhalbe mired and douſſed in diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etment and vexation. Let vnmarried people thinke of this, and be wiſe.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Secondly, I muſt aduiſe all married perſons, to grow acquainted with theſe duties, and to marke their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the ſame But miſtake me not. I would that the wife ſhould know hers, the husband his, and both the common duties. I deſire that they ſhould obſerue each their owne, not ſo much each others faylings. Indeed it may be feared, that diuers hearers now will bee worſe for hearing, becauſe they heard amiſſe. The husband may perhaps ring his wife a peale of her duty when hee comes home, and tell her how her faults were ript vp; and yet neuer conſider or meditate of his owne duties or faults. The wife alſo may likely tell him of his owne at home, when ſhe hath little or nothing to ſay to her-ſelfe. Thus both ſhall be worſe, when they ſeeke to vpbraide each other, not to amend each ones ſelfe. Thou husband didſt liſten attentiuely when the womans duties were handled, and thoughtſt, There he met with my wife; ſuch a time ſhee ſhewed little reuerence, leſſe obedience. Thou wife hadſt the like thoughts concerning thine huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: There hee told him home of his duty. It is not long ſince hee ſhewed himſelfe neither wiſe nor gentle. I would hee would ſee to amend. Vnwiſe man, vnwiſe woman: why hadſt thou not moſt care of thine owne ſoule? Couldſt thou marke what was good for anothers diſeaſe, not what for thine owne? Wilt thou grow skilfull in his way, and not know one foot of that wherein thy ſelfe muſt trauell? Brethren, ſiſters, let this be altered in vs. If thou be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian husband, haue more care to know that, and bee more frequent in conſidering that, for which thine owne ſoule muſt anſwer, then what lie, to the accounts of another. So doe thou that art a Chriſtian wife. And that man or woman that ſees not more faults and failings in him or her-ſelfe then the yoke-fellow, bewraies wondrous great pride, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1436:26"/>and hypocriſie, if hee or ſhee be not matched with one too too notorious for ill demeanours. If the heart were well touched, it owne ſinnes would bee more grieuous the husbands or wiues leſſe. Contend therefore, not how ſhort thy yoke-fellow comes, but not to come ſhort thy ſelfe. Paſſe by the others failings more eaſily, be more cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious towards thine owne: this were to deale as a Chriſtian, euen to iudge thy ſelfe. He neuer yet learnt to worke well in any work, that would caſt his eye more vpon his neighbors fingers than his owne. Neither was hee euer good ſcholler that would con his fellowes, and not regard the taske im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon himſelfe. And that makes husbands and wiues ſuch ill pay-maſters one another, becauſe they looke of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what is owing to them, not what they owe. I doubt not but experience will backe my ſpeech, if I pronounce that they be not the beſt husbands &amp; wiues, which are heard to complaine much of their yoke-fellowes defects in dutie, little of their own. And yet is not this ordinary? Euery man would be a good husband, if his wife were not ſo bad: &amp; ſhe a good wife, were not he ſo exceſſiuely faulty. Al the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, al the iudgings are datted at each other. What folly is this? Vnderſtand idle man and woman, it is not the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or receiuing of duty from others, but the knowing &amp; performing of what pertaines to thy ſelfe, that will proue thee a Chriſtian, comfort thee in temptation, reioice thee in death, and ſtand for thee in iudgment. And yet art thou ſoloud and much in calling for duty, ſo mute and dumbe and ignorant in yeelding it? To conclude therefore, know thine owne dutie beſt, marke moſt thine owne tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſings of duty; then ſhalt thou bee free from brawles with thy yoke-fellow, if thou be taken vp with paines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy ſelfe: and there is no better meanes of peace in families, than that euery one ſhould learne and ply his own worke, ſee and labour to mend his owne faults. Haue you then bene both or either vnchaſte, vnlouing, vnfaithful? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent both; and ſtraine not curteſie who ſhall beginne: but let either ſet other a copie of goodneſſe. And if you will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1436:27"/>needs ſtriue, let it be, which ſhall be the beſt, which mend firſt. Haſt thou bene a fooliſh, paſſionate, vniuſt husband, full of bitter words, perhaps alſo (which is monſtrous) of blowes in anger, ſeeking and ſeruing thy ſelfe alone, and not regarding thy wiues good, ſo thou mighteſt goe away with thine owne wil? Diue not into her faults, cry not out, ſhe hath bene thus and thus to me: but repent of thy bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnthriftines, folly of all ſorts: confeſſe it to God; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to make thee a better husband, that thy wife may bee better. Haſt thou bene a diſdainfull, contemptuous, brawling, impatient, diſcontented, and diſobedient wife? aske thine heare before God, and diſſemble nor. If yea, cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour not againſt thine husbands folly, exclaime not of his raſhnes and hardnes; but condemne thy ſelfe before, and call vpon God, to make thee feare and obey thine husband, as a Commander vnder him. Entreat him of mercy to make thee better, that thy husband alſo may be better. Follow the Prouerbe, and let euery of you mend one, I meane himſelfe, and contention wil ceaſe. Pray for each ones ſelfe firſt, then for each other. Where you haue offended, labour to ſee it, confeſſe, bewaile it, and call for power to reforme, and bee not skilfull to caſt the fault vpon another, but to caſt it out of thy ſelfe. So ſhall your loues bee ſure, your hearts comfortable, your example commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, your houſes peaceable, your ſelues ioyfull, your liues cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, your deaths bleſſed, and your memories happie for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="chart">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1436:27"/>
            <head>¶ The duties of the married <hi>people are either</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. Principall: the breach of which annihilates the former couenant by them made: which are
<list>
                     <item>1. The chaſte keeping of their bodies for each other: to which is oppoſed adulterie: ſect. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Cohabitation or dwelling together: to which is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deſertion: ſect. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Leſſe Principall: the breach whereof notwithſtanding, the comnant is firme: and theſe are of two ſorts:</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. Such as concerne their ordinary ſociety of life: which are either
<list>
                     <item>1. Mutuall: ſuch as both muſt mutually performe: which doe respect either
<list>
                           <item>1. Their perſons, and theſe are
<list>
                                 <item>1. Loue, ſect. <hi>7.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. Faithfulnes &amp; help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes conioyned, ſect. <hi>11.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Their families, as concerning their
<list>
                                 <item>1. Maintenance: ſect. <hi>13.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. Gouerning: ſect. <hi>14.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Speciall, pertaining to either ſeparately,
<list>
                           <item>1. The husband: whoſe duties are
<list>
                                 <item>1. To keepe his authority: ſect. <hi>15.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. To vſe his authority: of which I ſhew
<list>
                                       <item>1. The end: ſect. <hi>16.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2. The manner, with three vertues,
<list>
                                             <item>1. Wiſdome: ſect. <hi>18.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>2. Meeknes: ſect. <hi>21.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>3. Iuſtice: ſect. <hi>26.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. The wife: whoſe dutie is
<list>
                                 <item>1. To confeſſe her inferiority: ſect. <hi>27.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. To carry herſelfe as inferiour
<list>
                                       <item>1. In reuerence: ſect. <hi>29.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2. Obedience: ſect. <hi>34.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Such as concerne their ſociety in the marriage-bed, that it bee
<list>
                           <item>1. Louing. ſect. <hi>35.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Sanctified. ſect. <hi>35.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. Seaſonable. ſect. <hi>35.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
